<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ansuuere made by the noble lords the States, vnto the ambassadour of Polonia</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2245</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23189912</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23189912</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26361</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08087)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26361)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1800:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ansuuere made by the noble lords the States, vnto the ambassadour of Polonia</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Peter Geuaerts, dwelling in Lynbaeus Pat,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Amstersdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Giuen in Sgrauen Hage the 22. of Iuly. 1597"--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Poland.</term>
               <term>Poland --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26361:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26361:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <p>THE ANSVVERE made by the Noble Lords <hi>the States, vnto the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> of Polonia.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at Amſterdam by <hi>Peter Geuaerts,</hi> dwelling in Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeus Pat. Anno. 1597.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative design</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON. Imprinted by <hi>John Windet.</hi> 1597.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26361:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26361:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <head>
               <hi>Sigiſmundus</hi> the third by the grace of God King of Polonia. Great prince of Letawen, Duke of the Ruſsians, Pruſsians, Maſſawes, Samayts and Liefland, and King of Sweden and VVenden.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy, Honorable, noble, eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, famous, beloued and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We being mooued by many and true cauſes and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially by the conſideration of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> preſent eſtate of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Doe ſende to you the Honourable <hi>Pawel Van Dyialyn</hi> our Courtier. To the end you ſhould courteouſly &amp; willingly heare him in that which on your owne behalfes he is to propound. Which thing how bee it we aſſure our ſelues you wil performe of your owne accord, yet neuertheleſſe we earneſtly require you thereunto,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26361:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->
and doe offer vnto you euery way our Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and good-will.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Warſaw <date>the 19. of May, <hi>Anno</hi> 1597 in the tenth yeare of our Raigne in Polonia, and in our fourth yeare in Sweden.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Subſcribed <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmundus</hi> Rex.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The direction is. To the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Honourable Noble eſteemed and famous the States of the vnited Prouinces in the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, our beloued and eſpeciall.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:26361:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->
            <head>THE ANSWERE made by the Noble Lords and <hi>States, vnto the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> of Polonia.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He States generall of the vnited Prouinces with all dutifulneſſe, haue giuen eare vnto the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made by the Honourable <hi>Pawle Van Dyialyn</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the moſt excellent and puiſſant King of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia and Sweden. And vppon communication had concerning the ſame with the moſt excellent Prince and Councell of eſtate: Haue concluded to anſwere thereunto in briefe. <hi>Viz.</hi> That they verie willingly doe vnderſtand that his moſt excellent Maieſtie, ſo graciouſly wiſheth all good from God, vnto theſe vnited Prouinces. And for the ſame they in like manner by their prayer do wiſh vnto the ſaid moſt excellent and puiſſant King,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26361:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->
long life, faithfull Councell &amp; proſperous ſucceſſe, againſt the generall enemie of him and of all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>And as for that which the ſaide Honourable Lord Ambaſſadour furthermore did declare at large, touching the cruell warres of the Turke, howbeit the States here before by their many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident ſignes and other witneſſes haue had vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding thereof, yet his forces and the peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous dangers of Chriſtendome being now ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly repreſented before their eyes, doe make them exceeding much agrieued.</p>
            <p>Alſo the States be wholy of the ſame opinion and meaning with the ſaide moſt excellent and puiſſant King. That if (all debate being ſet aſide) the Kings and Princes did conioyne their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons and forces in one, (which in the deepeſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Chriſtendome hetherto yet neuer could be brought to paſſe.) That then Chriſtendom might lightly be freed from theſe miſchiefes.</p>
            <p>But it exceedingly grieueth the ſtates: That the ſaide moſt excellent King of Polonia and Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is ſo prepoſterouſly incenſed by the euill-willers of theſe Countries. That his Maieſtie ſhould thinke, that theſe warres which the ſayde States (being thereunto of neceſſitie forced) do maintain. Be the cauſe that the King of Spaine conuerteth not his Souldiours and Treaſures, for the ſuppreſſing of the Turke &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26361:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->
of Chriſtendome. For inſomuch as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the States, the cauſe why they maintaine theſe lamentable wars which already haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo many yeares: Hath beene long ſince more then ſufficiently vnto all Chriſtendome knowne, neither thinke they it now to be needfull nor do meane to ſet down here in many wordes, what the power is of Kings ouer or aboue their Subiects.</p>
            <p>But do <hi>(Signifie.)</hi> That theſe Low Countries (as publickly it is knowne) neuer had any Kings but onely Princes, as namely Dukes &amp; Earles, who haue beene tide and Lyable vnto Lawes, certaine, no leſſe then the people and ſubiects.</p>
            <p>Wherefore inſomuch as the K. of Spaine, theſe many yeares with intollerable tyrany, hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed theſe Countries, contrary to their aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent lawes and priueledges, by his owne oth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. And hath alſo without any iuſt cauſe, cauſed many hundred thouſandes of people to bee deſtroyed, and kept in hold, yea afterwards (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the lawes of all Nations) executed the Meſſengers of theſe countreyes that were men noble and of honor, ſent ouer into Spaine to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for an end of his cruelties, to be made. And moreouer afterwardes without conſent of the States, hath brought in new Taxations neuer harde of before, and baniſhed out of the Countrey an innumerable multitude of people of all man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of conditions and degrees. It is not to bee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26361:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->
wondred at, that (all Pariens being ouercome) in fine our God hath furniſhed weapons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vnder conduct of the right puiſſant Regent the noble Prince of Orenge: Firſt Holland and Seal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd, and then afterwardes the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces did reſcue, or franchiſed themſelues, which they haue taken in hande much latter then the continuall cruelties and tiranny of theſe Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards merited, and then the Princes and States of any other Prouinces woulde. Who woulde not for the ſhorteſt while haue ſuffered the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth part of thoſe miſchiefes and euils, which the inhabitants of theſe prouinces ſo many years ſince haue endured?</p>
            <p>And how be it that the States of their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loue towardes their Lordes, haue tryed all things that might tend to the auoyding of wars, and in like manner haue intended all meanes for peace, not onely by themſelues, but alſo that euen the Emperour, the Queenes Maieſty of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the King of Fraunce, and alſo the Germain Princes haue beene mediators therein. Yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the neerer could the ſame be brought to paſſe. Which is the cauſe that they perceyuing no more hope of any lawfull peace, and hauing to the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous loſſe of the Countries, learned that the king of Spayne vnder the cloake of intreaty for peace, did pretende to rent in ſunder the vnion of the countries, and to ſurpriſe the Townes, haue after the deſtruction of many men in wars, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26361:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->
of many Towns, and after many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of calamities ſuffred, beene conſtrained to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them to ſome other Counſell.</p>
            <p>And ſo what at all times hath beene free for all Nations, that they may caſt off from their neckes the inſupportable burthens yea of the Kinges themſelues, as many examples can make manifeſt. The ſame euer hath beene permitted and free for the free nation of the Lowe Dutch Countries, in proceeding to make a lawfull and neceſſary declaration, that the Lord of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is fallen from all his right, the which thing many yeares ſince hath beene not onely permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and concluded, but alſo by Edict or Placat publiſhed. After the which many of the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces condeſcended vnto the Duke of <hi>Alenſon</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the King of Fraunce to be their Lord, and did after his deceaſe (as alſo theretofore) vnder the gouernment of the ſaid right excellent Prince of Orenge, agaynſt the Spaniardes followe or proſecute the warres, and he being in villanous manner after the preſident of barbarous nations (through publike rewardes propounded by the Spaniardes) brought to his ende trayterouſly not in publike battell but at home. Alſo the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie they hauing recouered hope, that the affaires of theſe Countries woulde not onely come to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable commotion, but alſo fall to vtter ruine and decay: Yet the ſame notwithſtanding theſe Prouinces by the helpe of God Almighty) on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26361:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->
whome alone the States depend) haue vnder conduct of his moſt worthy ſonne Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> beene not onely protected, but alſo with his years encreaſed, growen, &amp; in their bounds enlarged.</p>
            <p>Now in that concerneth the King of Spaine, and his intent and hart (which beſt by his works may be knowne.) It is notorious that he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth nothing leſſe, then to warre againſt the Turke, but that he vnder colour of vpholding the Romiſh Religion, ſeeketh to raigne ouer all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes: For what els is or euer hath beene the cauſe of his warres againſt the moſt excellent Queene of England? What els hath moued him to ſtep into the French warres, and to ſeeke after the Kingdome of Fraunce? and to endeuour to withdraw or turne the Dukedome of Guylik and cleaue from their right Lordes and ſucceſſors, wherein he fewe Monthes ſince amongſt other his affaires tending to the ſame, hath delt with the Emperour by the Admirall of Arragon? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the ſubtill ſnares by him wrought againſt thoſe of Aken and Weſell, and more other Rijks eſtates and places, (if truth may be ſpoken:) But onely for to become ouer all thinges of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the vniuerſall Lorde? And for to attayne thereunto the onely drift of the king of Spayne is, that he vnder externall ſhewe of entreatie for peace might bring theſe Countreyes vnder his power with oppreſſion of their auncient lawes and priueledges, and ſet or place downe the ſeate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26361:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->
of his warres againſt the Princes of all king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes there. Where he ſhould find forces both by water and land and alſo money in a readineſſe.</p>
            <p>Which thing being by the Queenes moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſtie of England diſcretly conſidered of, ſhe as a defendor of true Religion many yeare ſince, is entred into League with theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
            <p>And wher in reſpect hereof lately, alſo is made a League betweene the King of Fraunce and the ſaid Queene of England: The ſaide vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces are alſo accepted in and vnto the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon the ſaid Lord Ambaſſador may eaſily vnderſtand, how inconuenient it is for the States in this conſtitution and ſhape of cauſes, to giue admonition of that which his Lordſhippe doth propound, eyther vnto the foreſaide Prince, or to the particuler States of the ſeuerall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially conſidering that they are inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſo manifold examples, that the enemy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth or practiſeth nothing but vnder the ſweet name of entreaty for peace, to cloake the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claps of warre, and to entrappe them vnwarily with deceat: Of the which the States hope his moſt excellent Maieſtie wil earneſtly take conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and not ſo much accompt of his affinitie with the K. of Spain, but that he rather wil awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp &amp; endeuour for the vantage and welfare of whole Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:26361:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 77 -->And in that the Lord Ambaſſador made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the letters of the moſt excellent King <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> his Maieſties prediceſſor. The ſame hath beene right acceptable, declaring very honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly that Kings Councell in the gouernment of his people and Subiects.</p>
            <p>And for ſo much as the States minde in heart nothing more, then to ſatiſfie all Kings touching the cauſes of theſe warres and other their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. Therefore they diligently haue anſwered the ſame letters to the ende they ioyntly might make manifeſt, how earneſtly they alwaies haue endeuored to continue the good will and loue of the King of Poland towards theſe Countries.</p>
            <p>In which earneſt deſire and will, they alwaies will perſeuere towards his moſt excellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, not doubting but that his Maieſtie will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringeably vpholde the mutable trafficke &amp; trade which cannot bee impeached ſo long as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lawes of all Nations in reaſon ſhall take place.</p>
            <p>For the reſt the ſaide States doe right hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly commend vnto his moſt excellent Maieſtie, the welfare and eſtate of theſe Prouinces and wil againe moſt earneſtly endeuour, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may not onely deſerue his Maieſties good will but alſo encreaſe the ſame towardes them.</p>
            <p>The States alſo doe beſeech the ſaid Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lorde Ambaſſador, earneſtly to ſignifie the ſame vnto his moſt excellent Maieſtie and louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26361:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 77 -->
to preferre theſe Countries, on which kindnes and ſeruice the ſtates will haue reſpect when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhall ſo require.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen in Sgrauen Hage <date>the 22. of Iuly. 1597.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26361:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 78 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
